<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Letter from Rochel in France to Mr. Demeuare, one of the French ministers at the French church in the Savoy, shewing the intolerable persecutions that are there exercised against them.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48074</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">27388118</idno>
  <idno type="VID">110097</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248531055</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1497</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R213301</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">27388118</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48074)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110097)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1725:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Letter from Rochel in France to Mr. Demeuare, one of the French ministers at the French church in the Savoy, shewing the intolerable persecutions that are there exercised against them.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet (2 p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Bentley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>"This is a true translation out of the original French"--p. 2.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">France. --  Edit de Nantes.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Huguenots --  France --  Poitou.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Protestants --  France --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Persecutions --  France.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>John Pas </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:110097:1"/>
            <head>A LETTER FROM Rochel in France, To Mr. <hi>Demeuare,</hi> one of the <hi>French</hi> Ministers at the <hi>French</hi> Church in the <hi>Savoy;</hi> shewing the Intollerable Persecutions that are there exercised against them.</head>
            <p>WHEREAS there is found upon Inquiry, That in the City of <hi>Westminster,</hi> and other Parishes of the County of <hi>Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dlesex,</hi> that there are now upwards of 3000 <hi>French</hi> Papists, which use several Handicraft Trades and Arts, as Taylors both for Men and Women, Chyrurgeons, Apothecaries, Shoomakers, Perriwig makers, Imbroiderers, Cooks, and other Trades, and several Serving Men, who by their Artifices and Contrivances have, and do their utmost endeavours to perswade People that there was no late Conspira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy against His Majesty and Protestant Religion, and Government of this Kingdom; and being not content therewith, also endeavour to maintain that there was no Powder Plot, nor any Massacre at <hi>Paris, Ireland,</hi> or any other places, of the Protestants, rendring the same ridiculous. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as there is now and hath been very great Cruelties and Persecutions in several parts of <hi>France,</hi> against those of the Reformed Religion, whereby several of them, to avoid the same, have deserted all their Concerns and Estates there, and for Refuge and Protection have retired themselves into <hi>England,</hi> under the Protection of his Majesty, and notwithstanding that it appears that the horrid Cruelties used in <hi>France</hi> against them are true, yet the Malice of those <hi>French Papists</hi> residing here do give out and maintain that there are no such Persecutions, but that those Persons who come over with their Wives and Children, are Criminals and Vagabonds, and such as are Bank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts, and prosecuted for their Debts in <hi>France,</hi> and who come over meerly to cheat their Creditors, and not for their Religion, as they pretend; Now to disabuse all good People, let them Consider, that in case such Persecutions had not been true, His most Excellent Majesty, and His most Honourable Privy Council (after due Examinations and Certificates proving the Truth thereof) would not have published His Royal Order, of the 28th of <hi>July</hi> 1681, in the behalf of all Persecuted Protestants abroad, nor incited such to come here for protection, nor recommended them to the good People of this Kingdom for a Charitable Collection for them, as by the said Order is at large Expressed: And for further Demonstration of the Rigour and barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Usage, now used against the Protestants at <hi>Rochel</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> I who am
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:110097:2"/>one of the Ministers of the <hi>French</hi> Church in the <hi>Savoy,</hi> have caused this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suing Letter to be Published, the Original whereof shall be produced if need requires.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>The said Letter is Dated at <hi>Rochel,</hi> the <hi>14th</hi> of <hi>December, 1681, New Stile,</hi> and is as followeth.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is now Eight days since that I writ to you, and told you that I should say nothing further concerning the Persecution in <hi>Poitou,</hi> having too great a subject of that which is now exercised in this Town, where the Prisons and Towers are filled with Men, Women, and Children, for, and by reason of their Religion, who are kept very close; where they allow them but Bread and Water, and not one Moity of so much as is sufficient for their subsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance: And besides, there is a constant Guard of Souldiers kept over them, who do hinder their Friends from giving them Assistance.</p>
            <p>There is an intention to make our Protestant Inhabitants of this Town to be responsible for the persecuted People who have deserted the Province of <hi>Poitou,</hi> and which have taken Shipping at this Sea-Cost, and gone out of this Kingdom; they have already Imprisoned Sixteen, and made Decrees against a quantity of the most considerable Persons, which have been obliged to absent themselves for to avoid Imprisonment. Mounsieur <hi>de Bompierre</hi> is one of the number; they pretend that he suffered some of those Persons who are gone to Forreign Parts to lye two Nights in the Out-Court of his House, which is near the Sea-Cost, until they had opportunity to Ship themselves. They have Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended and carried Prisoners to <hi>Trumpet</hi> Castle at <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> or to the Castle of <hi>Engoulesme</hi> (it is not yet known to which of the two) Mounsieur <hi>la Foretz</hi> of <hi>Mauze,</hi> Mounsieur <hi>de Boisatran</hi> of <hi>Nyort,</hi> Mounsieur <hi>Pain de Fon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenay,</hi> and Mounsieur <hi>Locquet</hi> of <hi>Marennes,</hi> all of them Ministers; and their Crime is, because they have Preached and Exhorted their Congregations to a perseverance in the Protestant Religion. We are now at that pass, that we know not what will become of us, being under the last Consternati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and upon the moment to be Massacred, if our Great God doth not avert that Blow; The Rabble being so annimated against us, in following the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the Lieutenant of these Parts, who hath now left off his Mask, that they are in a readiness to abandon themselves to all manner of Violence for to destroy us. We would willingly withdraw our selves as our Neighbours have done, but it is now too late; for the Sea-Costs are Guarded by Souldiers, who have Orders to kill and destroy all such Persons as they shall surprize in the Shipping of themselves: Fifteen days since they begun to put in Execution their Orders, and shot a Volley of Musquetoons upon several poor People that were Rowing in a Shallop, to go on Board an <hi>English</hi> Vessel, as Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sengers for <hi>London:</hi> There was a Seaman killed, and three Passengers wounded; my Prayers are to God, that I may not be obliged to tell you more by the next Post.</p>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>This is a True Translation out of the Original</hi> French.</p>
            </argument>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Bentley,</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>